RG 069:135, Richard F. Schneller Collection
Schneller (Richard F.) Collection
Connecticut State Library
Richard F. Schneller collection
1824-1996
bulk 1974-1988
Connecticut State Library
Schneller, Richard F.
16 cubic feet
Richard F. Schneller was a State Senator for the 20th District from 1975-1984. He worked on the 1986 O'Neill gubernatorial campaign as well as the 1984 Mondale presidential campaign and was the chairperson of the Governor's Building Construction Advisory Committee from 1987-1988.
RG069_135
2007-003
Biographical Note
Senator Richard F. Schneller, Democrat from Essex, Connecticut served in the State Senate representing the 20th District from 1975-1984. He was Senate Majority Leader from 1981-1984. Schneller was born in Essex on March 21, 1922. He attended Mount Hermon School and went on to obtain a Bachelor of Science degree from Yale University in 1943. Schneller then served in the Navy during World War II as a Lieutenant and was President of the Verplex Company from 1952-1972, which specialized in residential lighting manufacturing.
While in the State Senate, Schneller served on many committees including the State Urban and Development Committee as chairman (1975-1976), the Education Committee (1977-1978) and the Appropriations Committee (1979-1980). At the local level, Schneller served on the Essex Democratic Town Committee as chairman (1971-1978), the Essex Board of Finance, and the Regional District #4 Board of Education. He also served as trustee of the University of Connecticut (1958-1965), the Connecticut Conservation Association, Middlesex Memorial Hospital, the University of Connecticut Foundation, the Goodspeed Opera House, and the Mount Saint John School for Boys.
In 1984, Presidential candidate Walter Mondale called on Schneller to aid in his campaign in Connecticut. When Governor William O'Neill ran again for governor in 1986 he made a similar request to his good friend, after Schneller had retired from the Senate. Schneller was asked to chair the Governor's Building Construction Advisory Committee in 1987 whose primary focus was to evaluate building codes in Connecticut as a result of the L'Amibiance Plaza disaster in April of that year.
Scope and Content
The collection includes legislation material, speeches, correspondence, press releases, information pertaining to the Governor's Building Construction Advisory Committee, campaign material, news clippings, scrapbooks, and political cartoons.
Arrangement
Series 1. Legislation (1975-1985) contains both major state and personal legislation. This includes actual bills as well as background material.
Series 2. Speeches (1974-1985) contains speeches given by Schneller as well as a few speeches by others.
Series 3. Correspondence (1975-1985) contains both professional and personal correspondence including letters to and from other state legislators, governors and U.S. Congressmen.
Series 4. Press Releases (1974-1984) contains press material from Schneller's office detailing his professional life.
Series 5. Governor's Building Construction Advisory Committee (1970-1988) contains information on building and construction in Connecticut. A majority of the material relates to the L'Ambiance Plaza disaster of 1987. This includes news clippings, reports, Public Acts, notes, meeting material, correspondence and published material.
Series 6. Tax Commission (1981-1983, 1991) contains a small amount of material related to the commission of which Schneller was chairman.
Series 7. Campaigns (1981-1987) contains material related to both the 1984 Mondale presidential campaign and the 1986 O'Neill gubernatorial campaign including press releases, election results, issues, correspondence and financial material.
Series 8. News Clippings (1971-1983) contains 18 volumes of news clippings arranged in photo albums.
Series 9. Scrapbooks (1974-1996) is a collection of 9 scrapbooks arranged by Schneller's late wife Nancy which include photographs, news clippings, correspondence and ephemera.
Series 10. Political Cartoons (1979-1983) contains framed cartoons by Edmund S. Valtman (1914-2005) in which Schneller is featured.
Series 11. Published Material (1824-1933) contains material related to the General Assembly and Connecticut in general.
Related Material
RG002:025, Accession: 1999-013, Governor's Building Construction Advisory Committee.
RG005:036 Gov. Ella Grasso.
RG005:037 Gov. William A. O'Neill.
RG010, Accession: 2002-002, Insurance Department.Legal Division Files and Reports.L'Ambiance Plaza Settlements.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Construction industry--Safety regulations--United States--States; L'Ambiance Plaza (Bridgeport, Conn.); Legislators--Connecticut--Records and correspondence; Political campaigns
Persons:
Schneller, Richard F.; Mondale, Walter F., 1928-; O'Neill, William A. (William Atchison), 1930-
Places:
Essex (Conn.)
Occupations:
Legislators; Politicians
Document Types:
Bills (legislative records); Books; Broadsides; Clippings; Correspondence; Election returns; Notes; Pamphlets; Political cartoons; Press releases; Reports; Scrapbooks; Speeches
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
Richard F. Schneller assembled this collection himself with the help of his late wife Nance, who died in 2002. The Connecticut State Library acquired it from him on July 18, 2006.
Container List
- Series 1. Legislation, 1975-1985
  - Major State Legislation, 1975-1985
    - City and Town Development Act, 1975-1977, undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Coastal Area Management Program, 1983-1985, undated; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Connecticut Academy of Science and Engineering, 1976-1984; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Connecticut Conference of Municipalities, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
    - Connecticut Development Authority, undated (Box 1)
    - Connecticut Education Association, undated (Box 1)
    - Connecticut River Diversion, 1975-1978, undated (Box 2)
    - Conservation and Development, Plan for, 1976-1979, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Eagleton Institute of Politics, 1981-1985, undated; 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Episcopal Camp and Conference Center, 1983 April (Box 2)
    - Route 11, 1975-1984; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Satellite Vocational School, 1975-1984; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Southeastern Connecticut Tourism District, 1982 December 10 (Box 3)
    - Southwestern Area Commerce and Industry Association of Connecticut, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - State Colleges, 1979-1986 (Box 3)
    - State Senate, 1984 January-August (Box 3)
  - Personal Bills, 1975-1984 (Box 3)
    - Legislative Summary, 1975-1984 (Box 3)
    - 1975-1977, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 1978-1981, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - 1982-1984, 5 folders (Box 5)
- Series 2. Speeches, 1974-1985
  - Index, 1976-1984 (Box 5)
  - 1974-1976, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - 1977-1982, 11 folders (Box 6)
  - 1983-1985, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Speeches by others, 1985 November-December (Box 7)
- Series 3. Correspondence, 1975-1985
  - Legislative Correspondence, 1975-1985
    - Dodd, Christopher, 1981-1985 (Box 7)
    - Gejdenson, Sam, 1980-1985 (Box 7)
    - Grasso, Ella, 1978-1980; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - O'Neill, William (Box 7)
      - 1981-1982, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - 1983-1985, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Polinsky, Janet, 1976-1984 (Box 8)
    - Republican Party, 1984 February 2 (Box 8)
    - Secretary of the State, 1983-1984 (Box 8)
    - State Representatives, 1981-1984 (Box 8)
    - State Senators, 1981-1984; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Summer jobs, 1979 May 8, undated (Box 8)
    - United States Representatives, 1975-1984 (Box 8)
    - University of Connecticut Foundation, 1982 March 11 (Box 8)
    - Weicker, Lowell, 1975-1985 (Box 8)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 8)
    - 1982-1984, 2 folders (Box 8)
- Series 4. Press Releases, 1974-1984
  - 1974-1978 June, 15 folders (Box 9)
  - 1978 July-1980, 10 folders (Box 10)
  - 1981-1984, 10 folders (Box 11)
  - Radio and television, 1975-1980, undated (Box 11)
- Series 5. Governor's Building Construction Advisory Committee, 1970-1988
  - Bill and receipts, 1987 May-December (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1987 April-July (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1987 August-1988 (Box 12)
  - Meetings, 1987 May-December (Box 12)
  - News clippings, 1978-1988 (Box 12)
  - Notes, 1987-1988, undated (Box 12)
  - Organizational material, 1980-1988, undated (Box 12)
  - Press releases, 1987 May, undated (Box 12)
  - Promotional material, undated (Box 12)
  - Public Acts, 1988 (Box 12)
  - Public hearings, 1987 November-December (Box 12)
  - Reports, 1970-1988; 5 folders (Box 13)
- Series 6. Tax Commission, 1981-1983; 1991
  - General, 1981-1983 (Box 13)
  - Newsclippings, 1982-1983, 1991 (Box 13)
- Series 7. Campaigns, 1981-1987
  - Walter Mondale Presidential Campaign, 1983-1985 (Box 14)
    - General, 1984 August-October, undated (Box 14)
    - Ace Printing, 1984 August-October (Box 14)
    - "America for Mondale", 1983-1984, undated (Box 14)
    - Connecticut Democrats '84 (Box 14)
      - General, 1984 August-November, undated (Box 14)
      - Audio Recording, undated (Box 14)
      - Letterhead and Envelopes, undated (Box 14)
    - Contact list, undated (Box 14)
    - Correspondence, 1984 August-October, undated (Box 14)
    - Dodd, Christopher, 1984 August 10 (Box 14)
    - Election results, undated (Box 14)
    - Ferraro, Geraldine A., 1984 August-October (Box 14)
    - Financial, 1984-1985; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Issues, 1984 January (Box 15)
    - Issues, 1984 February-September, undated (Box 15)
    - Position papers, 1983 February-December, undated (Box 15)
    - Press releases, 1984 October 15 (Box 15)
    - Selwyn and Associates, 1984 August-October, undated (Box 15)
    - Speeches, 1984 September 25 (Box 15)
    - State campaign, 1984 August-November, undated (Box 15)
    - Super Tuesday, 1984 March 13 (Box 15)
  - Willaim O'Neill 1986 Gubernatorial Campaign, 1981-1987 (Box 15)
    - General, 1981-1986, undated; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - General, 1986 March-November, undated; 4 folders (Box 16)
    - Debate material, 1986 September-October (Box 16)
    - Delegates, 1986 June-July, undated (Box 16)
    - Democratic State Convention, 1986 July 2-18, undated (Box 16)
    - Financial, 1986 September 2 (Box 16)
    - Minority and "Get Out the Vote" material, 1985-1987, undated (Box 16)
- Series 8. News Clippings, 1971-1983
  - 1971 August, 1973 June-1974 September, 1 volume (Box 17)
  - 1974 May-July, 1 volume (Box 17)
  - 1974 June-October, 1 volume (Box 17)
  - 1974 September-December, 1 volume (Box 17)
  - 1975 January-April, 1 volume (Box 17)
  - 1975 April-November, 1 volume (Box 17)
  - 1975 November-1976 March, 1 volume (Box 17)
  - 1976 March-August, 1 volume (Box 18)
  - 1976 August-December, 1 volume (Box 18)
  - 1976 December-1977 May, 1 volume (Box 18)
  - 1977 May- 1978 April, 1 volume (Box 18)
  - 1978 April-November, 1 volume (Box 18)
  - 1978 October-1979 February, 1 volume (Box 18)
  - 1979 February-June, 1 volume (Box 18)
  - 1979 July-1980 January, 1 volume (Box 19)
  - 1980 February-June, 1 volume (Box 19)
  - 1980 June-December, 1 volume (Box 19)
  - 1980 November-1981 June, 1 volume (Box 19)
  - 1981 April-November, 1 volume (Box 19)
  - 1981 October-1982 August, 1 volume (Box 19)
  - 1982 March-1983 September, 1 volume (Box 19)
- Series 9. Scrapbooks, 1974-1996
  - 1974-1975, 1 volume (Box 20)
  - 1976-1977, 1 volume (Box 20)
  - 1978-1979, 1 volume (Box 20)
  - 1979-1980, 1 volume (Box 21)
  - 1980-1982, 1 volume (Box 21)
  - 1982, 1 volume (Box 21)
  - 1983-1984, 1 volume (Box 22)
  - 1984-1987, 1 volume (Box 22)
  - 1988-1996, 1 volume (Box 22)
- Series 10. Political Cartoons, 1979-1983
  These framed cartoons are by Edmund S. Valtman (1914-2005).
  - "This Is My Formula for Equalized School Funding", 1979 (Box 23)
  - General Assembly leaders, including Schneller, playing musical chairs, 1980 (Box 24)
  - Schneller sharpening hatchets being given to General Assembly members entering a budget hearing, 1980 (Box 24)
  - Schneller and another man both on the Senate Majority Leader chair as Joseph Lieberman, outgoing Senate Majority Leader, looks out window with telescope toward the U.S. Capitol, 1980 (Box 24)
  - Schneller and Murphy trying to control Senate Democratic Caucus as represented by a donkey, 1981 (Box 25)
  - "We Have To Do Something Before We All Get Drowned", 1981 (Box 25)
    Concerns the volume of legislative bills.
  - "Can It Be Remodeled or Should It Be Razed and Built Anew?", 1982 (Box 25)
    Concerns the tax structure. Schneller was chariman of the Tax Commission.
  - "The Great Juggling and Balancing Act,", 1983 (Box 25)
    Concerns the budget.
- Series 11. Published Material, 1824-1933
  - Connecticut Register (Hartford: F.A. Brown, 1858 ). (Box 26)
  - Barber, John Warner. Connecticut Historical Collections (New Haven, Conn.: Durrie & Peck and J.W. Barber, 1838 ). (Box 26)
  - Legislative Roll and Lodgings, 1824 May; framed broadside (Box 26)
  - Pocket Manual: Roll, Committees and Rules of the General Assembly of Connecticut, 1933 (Box 26)
  - Report of the Comptroller of Public Accounts, to the General Assembly, May Session, 1866 (Hartford: Case, Lockwood and Company, 1866 ). (Box 26)